okay tonight's the big night we do Rick
come okay Buddha Buddha nature Buddha
Essence and uh we got a lot to cover
tonight so I'm going to kind of Go Fast
and we might go a little bit late sorry
um well okay but tonight we we actually
do the rang luk our own system on what
is Buddha nature so again to remind you
this month class number six was ideas
from the utara Tantra about Buddha
nature and how it's concealed and why
it's concealed and angles from which
it's
revealed and then this class the second
of the three is about Rick meaning what
is the classical presentation our
classical presentation of Buddha nature
you know so that'll be covered in four
parts uh what is the proof from
scripture about the idea of Buddha
nature like where do you get this idea
of Buddha nature from scripture um
second part was what was that uh
definitions of Buddha nature you know
like classical presentation of Buddha
nature I miss something in
there well we'll figure it
out uh then the third part would be uh
what was
that let me look the fourth one I can
tell
you uh anyway uh fourth one is going to
be there's a very very interesting um
tantric presentation of uh Buddha nature
so I thought to throw that
in uh and then I what was the third one
let me see hang on
yeah oh okay what did I say was the
first
one yeah that's not the first one first
one is uh different names for Buddha
nature okay like in the scriptures you
see a whole bunch of different names for
Buddha nature so I thought I'd go over
them so first we get different names for
Buddha nature then we get classical
scriptural references both by the Buddha
and by later people and then thirdly we
get the classical presentation what are
the different types of Buddha nature
stuff like that and then fourth one will
be um sort of a special tantric take on
Buddha nature okay how Buddha Nature's
developed okay well anyway uh names for
Buddha nature generally they're going to
have two parts each one of them and the
first part is pretty inter it's like
three different words for Buddha right
but really what we're really interested
in is all different names for nature but
you might get Buddha nature those who
have gone thus nature those who have
gone to Bliss nature and so the first
three names are pretty much
interchangeable so I'm just going to
write them um well we'll start with the
first one
St
I'm going to put also the Sanskrit
pronunciation and then you'll get the
Sanskrit writing from Christy La who's
going to do the Sanskrit for this class
and the last class a week from tonight 6
o' p.m. okay so you coming early next
Wednesday which will be the the next and
last class of this month on utara Tantra
you come an hour early if you want the
Sanskrit and you'll get two classes of
Sanskrit okay so I'll just put the
pronunciation
and this is just if you're you know if
you're teaching Rick in 200 in October
come right you should know the different
words and then you should know the
Sanskrit they come up a lot you see them
a lot of people because it's so hard to
come up with a English word for Buddha
nature or Buddha essence or Buddha seed
or whatever people sometimes just say
tataba um the accent is actually long
here so it's taga say taga
uh th is an unfortunate transliteration
of um Sanskrit as opposed to T see this
is T this is T it's
not okay it's not t or t or gy
tharin okay uh it's tatag Gara say one
more time
T okay good umin
which is t means like that just that way
just that
way G which is she means gone gone that
way
okay then uh
ninbo which means I'm going to translate
it tonight as
Essence means Garba is for Garba
okay um this is the ninbo that you see
in the hard Sutra sh for example and it
can be translated as heart or Essence
okay and um we're going to talk more
about that in a minute but Garba I
thought you'd like to know the the
literal sense of it because then if you
know the Sanskrit you get a better sense
of it g what would you guess the English
cognate
is Gard um keep the B Sound garbage
maybe but I don't know uh put the G and
the r put the r after the G
dark grab okay gra grab grab in Sanskrit
means to grab and what it means it came
from an ancient word for womb and the
idea is that the seed is what do you
call it catches in the womb and then the
baby starts to grow like we say in
English I think catch the seed catches
in the womb and then there's um what do
you call it
uh an embryonic Journey yeah when the
what do they call that uh the very
beginning conception conception yeah the
moment of conception well concepti right
uh is uh is to grab it means you catch
and then you start to grow okay see idea
is that Gara means Womb you see it means
the hold the hold even in um the hard
Sutra where is the hard Sutra Tau
taught yeah Raj G has the same root
which means the keep of the king or the
hold of the king Raja GHA means the
king's uh the place where the king holds
holds power Raja GHA um and reg comes
from Raja and Regal and Royal and all
those words so anyway Gaba means the
womb uh the the Buddha womb okay get the
feeling of it and then the Tibetans
chose to translate that as ningo meaning
essence or heart okay so you start to
get a feeling of what all the meanings
that are floating around here it's nice
to see the Sanskrit and the Tibetan
okay here's number two you're going to
be asked on the homework to give three
of them out of five so you can turn off
after the third
one cards to the four different answer
for so AR eight oh it's going to be
something like that you can you can mix
them mix and match okay yeah
uh oh I didn't put the tat there oops
okay the master has a boo
boo uh
go
that's why it's
hot come
here that's the camir bird come
come
here
say the last one was what in
tibetan and now we got almost the same
right a little bit different in in
Sanskrit sugat Garba say sugat gar okay
Garba again is the same sense of the
womb
uh sugata means gone well or gone to
happiness and it can mean either
uh went somewhere in an easy way or or a
flow nice flow like PE this ref it's the
name for the Buddhist right Desa and
tagata are just names for Buddhas those
who have gone that way those who have
gone to happiness those who have gone to
Bliss those who have gone well so Su
means well g means gone G came into
English to gum became
come uh and then sue came
into IND IND European is U ESU the S
dropped down of Greek and it
became the U in euthanasia
euphonic Ur
rhythmics all right yeah okay so this
this is found in Greek as EU because it
came from an old indipan ESU so it means
good good gone womb and the Tibetans
translated that as uh the essence of
those who have gone happily or well uh
I'm going to call this yeah I'm going to
keep calling it Essence okay is gone
like g g is
got the you know Gone Gone really gone
that's the heart sura Mantra right okay
that was the second one right here's the
third one what is the third
one e that's a
mess oh okay here's a th one
a hand broker
you
say sound
familiar okay now you get something
really interesting this is my
advertisement I spent uh last week at
Arts house we really had a good time but
um in how and uh he's like adamant that
people should get some Sanskrit under
their belt you know as if it's not
enough to spend 20 years on your Tibetan
but um this is a case where the Tibetans
use the same translation for a different
Sanskrit word you see the
Tibetans uh only had one word for heart
and
Essence uh whereas the Sanskrit was two
different words so here you get a nice
feeling for how cool it will be like in
the tant course when we get to the we're
going to do a lot of the tant course in
Sanskrit from Sanskrit
Originals um and then you'll get more of
a gut feeling for it because our
language comes from Sanskrit okay so
tagata is the same gone that way meaning
Buddhas and then
Hera uh
uh guess what word comes from this part
of
it heart heart directly comes from Hera
okay heart the heart of the Buddhist
okay uh so now you got a new word for
Buddha nature heart Buddha heart Buddha
heart okay literally the this the sh NBO
is
called the heart of the essence of the
the heart of the Perfection of wisdom is
the real name of the heart Sutra okay
and that's straight from
Hera
okay but the rest is all the same in
tibetan right so here you have a case
where uh which is actually not that
common where if you know the Tibetan the
Sanskrit could have been two different
things and you might hear two different
words and then you really get a
different feel don't you I mean a womb
and a heart is a different thing in a
way but um but in a way they're the same
aren't they so kind of cool is that is
that Bliss uh no this is the one that
means they have gone that way they Tata
t means gone that
way oh tan sorry yeah it means like that
like that
okay let me see what's the next one
who's that girl who's that Lazy Girl
[Music]
okay number four
say Rick Rick you gotta roll the r
ruffles have rides I can't do it though
rii yeah it's not done with your front
teeth on your lower lip it's done by
flopping your tongue inside Rick yeah
good uh and then in Sanskrit
gotra yeah um Rick means in tibetan like
family or
type uh
from
what BN into yeah where does it come
from batara is found in the tunduk site
six times a day right
and okay and it's the and it's the basis
for when you take you
say today I've been born into the Rick
of the Buddhas meaning the the
Buddhist thus I have become a child of
the
Buddhas now no matter what from today I
will try to act in accordance with my
family I won't try to I'll try not to
embarrass my family basically okay um
gotra now let's see how they got that
from gotra right gotra means a u cattle
pen go means cow okay Gua came into
English as cow
also as uh what's another word for Bine
is connected to this and then means to
protect and it's found in the root for
Tara Tara meaning the one who carries
you be out of trouble dma okay so it's
the same roote so go means a uh cow
protection which means a uh pen a pen or
a fence together yeah and then it over
the centuries it became a word for um
family you see cuz it was everyone in
the same pen you see yeah same her or
something like that the word Gama Buddha
Gama means highest go highest cow and
that's an idea of the head head ball of
the herd which you ever which if you
ever met one at Diamond Mountain West
you'd understand you know like the other
cows are about this tall Maybe This Tall
on the back but the bull out there was
like this like I think 5T tall and the
his back was 5T and like if you ran into
him one night it was really scary but
Gama means that head B um so gotra means
it came to mean family you see and when
the Tibetan translators in 1000 ad had
to struggle with a word they said Rick
family okay like Buddha family okay um I
like to call it maybe I'm going to call
it family seed okay I'll tell you why
we're going to come up with a lot of
problems with translating Rick tonight
Rick is a big subject tonight Rick and
Comm are synonyms okay I mean in most
Buddhist scriptures you'll see Comm I
think uh my needed to cut uh syllables
but uh you'll see more common is Rick
than C okay um okay next one
I'm going to go back on page because I
want to add something okay ready
remember
g go back one page leave three blank
Pages 6 days from now we'll get back to
that uh up here I want to add
s key
sayi
Ricki Rick Rick um now we get a third uh
word to put in front of the front part
of Buddha nature right we had you know
essence of those gone thus and essence
of those gone to Bliss and now we have
essence of Buddha okay or uh family seed
of Buddha or something like that okay
what I'm saying is that you can replace
any of the first three you could say
Buddha you could say those gone to Bliss
you could say those gone that way it
doesn't matter you can mix them up
doesn't matter but that's the third one
okay I'm going to stop putting the first
half now okay so we're up to come say
come
okay not much to say I would call it
Buddha I'm just kind of artificially
trying to distinguish them from each
other Buddha part maybe Buddha part da
means to set down something we find it
in the word deed like a written document
that's been set down and agreed to by
everybody we find it in the word fact
when you get from Sanskrit to Greek the
DH changes to F so so you find words
that mean like set down
fixed finished okay it's like the Parton
you which is a Buddha here you should
get this kind of vision of uh marble
under the Earth or something you know
like something really substantial under
your flesh that's the idea like the
steel core of your being the Diamond
core of your being is like d come and
from that the Buddha will grow you know
that will trigger the Buddha the growth
of the Buddha of your buddhahood
okay and there's one more what was
[Music]
that I got to hang
on this is just another Sanskrit word
for Rick
say Rick Rick van v v van okay Vana
means uh it's an old word for bamboo and
for a certain kind of plant and so it
means a a a a a plant family uh Mercedes
suggested me the word uh genus g n u s
like or what would be a word David I
don't
know a a group of a Botanical group
families yeah family or species
yeah yeah species would be the last okay
it's almost like a species or no no it
wouldn't be species right it'd be a
family family like a plant family or an
animal family or a type or a genus of
okay but there you get the feeling Vana
came from a word for a group of plants
that were grouped together into a family
so again it's this idea of a a Genus or
genealogy or a group okay so a family
but also the seed from which this family
Springs and the womb and the essence and
the heart and those are all the words
for Buddha nature and you have to
explore them like go home and think
about it you know all those feelings of
a Diamond core womb a heart Essence
family seed family uh I like Gene
actually for Rick you know because it
gives both feelings of a genus and a
seed you know uh a family and the seed
from which the family grows you see I
mean so all of those are Buddha nature
okay all of those you start to get a
feeling for what Buddha nature means in
the native languages okay
you also get a you get an interesting
insight into the limitations that the
Tibetans were faced with sometimes like
sometimes they clarified one Sanskrit
word by splitting into three different
Tibetan words sometimes they were faced
with two different Sanskrit words and
didn't have different words and used one
word and then we lost something when
that happened you see when it came down
to us in in a foreign language okay so
it's good to have both available
especially when you get into Tantra
especially when you get into the inner
body it's very useful to have the
Sanskrit because there are so it's like
17 kinds of words for snow and Eskimo
you know like slush snow uh second level
slushy snow third level slush snow snow
mixed with water and when you get to
Tantra it's like 10 different
distinctions of your central channel
that are made in Sanskrit but not
necessarily in tibetan so as you'll find
this weekend we'll be getting into a lot
of the older sources for for our tantric
studies
um okay now I want to go into sources
for Buddha nature you know this is all
setting up for next week right which is
what what's the third part of this class
on Buddha nature going to be we're gonna
have arguments from other schools and I
thought um I found I also pulled out
arguments from ancient India you're
going to get the bashiko or the ABI
Dharma version of of Buddha nature then
you're going to get the sutris or the
logic school ver version of Buddha
nature then you're going to get the mind
only version of Buddha nature which are
all different from the one you're
studying tonight which is the ultimate
version right uh then we're going to
throw in um early Tibetan uh wise sages
their version of Buddha nature and
emptiness that carried in a strong
carried on in a strong tradition up to
the present time in some of the Tibetan
Traditions so three ancient schools on
Buddha nature and one uh very strong
uh Tibetan school that was competing
with Jetson capa's presentation of
emptiness okay um and I thought it'd be
good for you to get it from the horse's
mouth so you'll be reading the original
texts by those schools okay uh you'll
get their own text they get to speak for
themselves which is not always the case
in a in a debate in the monastery okay
uh and so if you're on our side which we
get to be tonight right it's called Rong
Luke we're wearing galupa hat tonight
yellow hat
tonight
um you want to be able to pull out
original scriptural proofs for Buddha
nature right being
emptiness and then uh later we'll get
into the the logical proofs but we start
with scriptural proofs Lord Buddha said
this Arya mraa said this um harib badra
who wrote the greatest commentary on um
M tra's Works um about 600 years after a
you're going to get his version these
three are all accepted by all Tibetan
schools okay so if you get in a debate
you can either pull the logic hat out or
you can pull out the scriptural proof
hat uh but if somebody says oh Buddha
nature is not something negative you're
going to have three uh kinds of
ammunition to pull out Lord Buddha 500
BC um my tra 350 ad uh Master har ra uh
800s sometime in the 800s okay before
and then after that Buddhism comes to
Tibet and then we can't argue anymore
because that's our own you know that
would be like starting to get into jetsu
capus uh version so like when we debate
inter Monastery debate like Jong versus
Sarah uh we can't use Sarah textbooks
you see we can only use earlier texts by
Jessa or earlier you see so it depends
on what group you're in you got be able
to go back to a sources which are
accepted by both parties so that's what
we're going through next we're going to
go through three sources accepted by all
tetan parties okay so if you ever get a
hot argument with somebody from another
tradition about is Buddha nature
emptiness or is Buddha nature an already
existing Buddha inside of you or is
Buddha nature um something physical
thing in like some kind of blue light
inside stuff like that you can get you
can say no look look look we had that
back in
utar tant course here's the reading
here's three quotations from Lord Buddha
a okay we're going to go through those I
want you to memorize them if you're
doing Tibetan track they're not very
long they're just like little tiny
sentences um they're very short so
here's the first
one this is from the 20,000
verses which is equals the middle
length
suture on
the
Perfection of
wisdom for
[Music]
this
ready say
ring this is the famous place where Lord
Buddha begins to talk about Buddha
nature okay in the Perfection of wisdom
what's the shorter length Sutra how long
is that 8,000 8,000 versus what's the
longer length version 100,000 100,000
they say that those were all the short
one in the old days and they lost the
others 100,000 verse presentation of
perfection wisdom is the well used to be
the short one then it got lost so now
that all we have left okay it's see
enough um tell me who's
RJ sabti okay where from the Diamond
Cutter okay he's like the Fall Guy for
Lord Buddha right who's he in
Disguise Mai in disguise right so so
Lord Buddha is addressing probably subi
has asked a question and Lord Buddha is
saying RoR which means subti okay namka
SK Sky La J I don't think you know J
means a footprint or a track or a trail
left by a jet plane or what do you call
those things Contra contrail it means
like that or a deer track it's called a
J or a footprint is called a j or those
places where you see the Lord Buddha has
has put his hand like the Chinese
restaurant in
Hollywood uh you know those are all
called J J okay sometimes they call LJ
JJ means handprint okay uh
Jay I'm sorry oh CH this I'm sorry this
J means birds bird apostrophe s Birds
track Bird's trail trail of a bird who's
flying through the sky
right the contrail left by a bird flying
to the sky
okay doesn't exist you can't see
anything that doesn't exist ching and
mimo invisible can't see it can't see
it it doesn't exist then you can't see
it so the second J here doesn't mean
Lord the first J means of a bird and the
second J means uh track okay
those of you know Tibetan it's the word
after right like Jumba or something like
that um J Jang for Anu but anyway um now
I got to tell you where what Lord Buddha
is referring to Lord Buddha is referring
to the path of
preparation okay Lord Buddha is
referring to the path of preparation
more
specifically uh Lord Buddha is referring
to the first of the four steps in the
path of preparation first of the four
levels which is
called TR
say what's the last one CH say
again CH taught it to us so many times
it's just like a MTO in my brain you
know I don't have to think about it true
means inner heat heat it means you're
getting hot it means for what seeing
emptiness yeah seeing emptiness directly
getting hot warming up okay so Lord
Buddha is talking about the first of
those levels he goes on through 12 more
levels
okay but I'll just tell you the first
six because that's
easy okay this one here's the heat level
yeah he's talking about heat level from
the path of
preparation he could just as well have
been talking about Peak which is the
second
Lama Mastery which is the third Lama
highest thing in the universe which is
the fourth level then what comes after
that path of seeing number
five and then path of habituation number
six let's stick with those six he goes
through seven more but I don't want to
do it tonight
okay I'll say it again six deep
realizations you can have in your
spiritual
career this thing about the bird not
leaving in his track conil in the sky
when they pass by is talking about the
first of those six which is he
what's happening at heat what's
happening at the path of preparation
studying emptiness intellectual
understand understandings of emptiness
not
direct but you're thinking about
emptiness you know you're starting to
get it you know like from these classes
you you get pretty good Jon preparation
from these classes you know okay I got
it I understand what emptiness is not
and I understand what emptiness is okay
especially with objects and subjects you
know during the path of preparation
you're starting to get hot you're
getting close Okay hot like
that let's talk about the emptiness that
do you perceive
emptiness not intellectually you got to
say yeah you do intellectually you know
somebody says do you perceive in
oparation you go yeah and then you let
them squirm you know I mean let them
prove to you why not you know yeah you
perceive it but logically logically
through thinking through
contemplation
okay any special what kind of
emptiness we never got into that we
never got into that there's two schools
of thought I mean there's a big debate
about it but one is oh just kind of
emptiness in general okay like when I
stand up here and talk about emptiness
you are perceiving emptiness you're
having an inkling of emptiness that's a
correct perception for for that um
mental picture of emptiness that you
have it's not the direct perception
emptiness but it's correct it's okay
it's it's pretty good okay it's airtight
logically okay General emptiness but
then some schools say when you are
thinking about
emptiness uh and you're perceiving
emptiness in a way can we say You're
perceiving The Emptiness of your
thinking about
emptiness
no why not because you
have just thinking is a POS no but how
about as an intellectual thing can I say
that when you think about
emptiness could you be thinking about
the emptiness of that thought sure that
would be almost very natural right if
the first emptiness you ever see
directly is the emptiness of me then it
might be natural to say that the first
emptiness you see on the path of
preparation is the emptiness of your
thinking about emptiness The Emptiness
of your own mind The Emptiness of your
own thoughts okay and in that sense we
could say that that emptiness provides
the
foundation for Mahayana achievements
from Mahayana
spiritual uh realizations and that's how
Emptiness is
presented with regard to Rick I'll say
it
again that emptiness which provides the
foundation for all the realizations you
get on the five
paths can be called a rick in a way okay
that's the emptiness that you're
thinking about really the best what he's
trying to say is the best kind of
emptiness that you can think about when
you're thinking about Emptiness is how
about thinking about you thinking about
emptiness and your
emptiness and The Emptiness of your own
thoughts as you're thinking about
emptiness why am I having this thought
about
emptiness yeah or or I have the virtue
I'm projecting this thought about I'm I
got enough virtue
godamn massive virtue I got that much
virtue to be projecting myself thinking
about emptiness okay like if you get in
a fight about EMP with somebody you're
already into
99.9999999% of anyone who ever lived
lucky you know cuz you're thinking about
it to be projecting for Michael to
project Michael sitting around the table
with coffee talking about emptiness to
somebody is extraordinary virtue
extraordinary projection you know so
let's talk about that emptiness you know
that's empty too you could have been
talking about last week's movies you
could have been talking about TV shows
God I did three weeks of this you know
no you get on AOL comes up new movie
star new TV star new movie new TV star
rock and roll star you know over and
over and there's nothing else you know
and it's like how many new TV stars can
you have oh they're endless you know
they just keep like this you know and
you know to What's The Emptiness of
thinking about emptiness you see it's so
cool to have that projection you know if
you want to think about emptiness think
about how cool it is to be thinking
about emptiness that's a that's a good
emptiness thinking about that emptiness
would provide a basis for for all
Mahayana achievements so whenever Lord
Buddha talked about emptiness with
regard to come Buddha nature he talked
about the emptiness that you're looking
at as you go through those six
incredible levels heat Peak Mastery
highest
Dharma path of seing path of habituation
what's the emptiness of those you know
what's the emptiness of your state of
mind
which if you're really uh in it in if
you're really up for it if you're really
in it you should be looking at the
emptiness of that thought
itself okay and that's Buddha nature
that's so cool that's really what will
is a womb for Buddha that's the heart of
Buddha you want someplace to justatee
your Buddha man think about the
emptiness of thinking about the
emptiness you know and that's called
duid then say dupen Foundation of all
Mahayana
attainments t d and it's a big subject
in a it's one of Aang's favorite
subjects you know what is the foundation
for all higher realizations think about
emptiness what
emptiness which
emptiness The Emptiness of those
realizations I'll say it again you know
where's a good place to where's a good
womb in which to jate conceive and jate
your Buddha Buddha you to come
right think about the emptiness of your
thoughts of
emptiness think about the emptiness of
your thoughts of emptiness which is to
say think about your own
emptiness that provides the foundation
for all spiritual attainments okay it's
the emptiness of thinking about
emptiness that is the real seed for
buddh okay because that that thinking
about emptiness can change into the
direct perception of EMP which later
changes into the Buddhist
body you see so that's the real womb you
know that's so cool you know so that's
whenever Rick comes up it comes up in
this context what's the emptiness of
those six
realizations what's the emptiness of
those six stages what's the emptiness of
my own mind when I'm thinking about
emptiness what's the emptiness of me
when I'm thinking about emptiness and
that's Rick see it's so cool just comes
back on itself like that if you want
something that's going to trigger
buddhahood in you that's it think about
your own emptiness as you're thinking
about emptiness okay uh that's what this
refers to okay
um there's no Trail there's no you can't
see it what's
mate8 non objectifying compassion yeah
which is the first part of Jus Mantra
okay uh I bow to the person with love
that sees nothing sees nothing what do
you mean sees nothing it looks at
sensient beings and sees their emptiness
okay so mimik is a code word ever since
Buddha two and a half thousand years ago
for what don't see anything for
emptiness for the dire perception of
emptiness okay ever since 2 and half
thousand years
ago same thing you don't see anything
look up lots of birds travel between the
spring and somewhere down there I never
where they're going but they go by this
house like crazy all day long it's very
beautiful you know bright yellow bright
white red and um they pass and you don't
see anything after they've gone there's
nothing there anymore you know and
Buddha's saying you know your nature is
like that you can't see it you just
can't see it it's like the trail of a
bird you know it's emptiness okay so
from the very
beginning Lord Buddha spoke about Buddha
nature in terms of can't see any
anything and it's connected to each of
the six paths in the reading you'll get
the other 13 12 okay or five I'm making
it short tonight the first six are the
biggest but then you'll get a beautiful
um comparison for The Emptiness of your
mind at second level of path of
preparation then the emptiness of your
mind at third level path of preparation
and then the emptiness of your mind at
the fourth level path of preparation the
last of the 13 total is the emptiness of
the of
Rick The Emptiness of Bud nature
okay so obviously we're on the right
track this is where the Buddha mentioned
these things from the P
to Invisible that yeah yeah yeah is is
Emptiness is a negative is an absence
there ain't no track there okay like
that yeah KLA could you just put
together the translation of the oh yeah
I'm sorry let's go through it
oy
Ooty okay
uh when a I'm just going to do a free
translation OAB buy when a bird flies
through the
sky it doesn't leave any track you can't
see any
track okay that's all that's a reference
to The Emptiness of your mind at the
first level of the path of
preparation
okay uh what did I promise you next what
Authority would satisfy any
anybody past Buddha is pretty
good how about a future Buddha okay this
is from my tray this is from the
ornament of
realizations is one of the
whatook yeah one of the five books that
was given by whom to
whom my song during his trip to uh TOA
which took how long you get the reading
tonight by the
way 50 to 53 years human time uh a
morning God God time God Realm time okay
uh this is the F abis Anar for those of
you who care okay and he says we had to
memorize this when I was a
kid
[Music]
for
for for
okay here we
[Music]
go okay TOA means
what realization it's a synonym
for l l and Toba are synonyms when we
say five paths we're really talking
about five stages of realization right
but he says
CH what's tund
succession yoga chuk means the six the
six dharmas
okay if you want to get into those
things those six realization here just
ch just mean things Juke means get into
it if you want to get into those six
realizations which six sound familiar
from above yeah
yeah okay four stages of the path of
preparation path of scene path of
habituation to start again there's seven
more which is the dot dot dot there I
left it out cuz I didn't want you to be
here till midnight 10:00 is okay okay
there's seven more the last one happens
to be Rick itself but anyway juk if you
want to get into those six realizations
you need a foundation then you need to
someplace that everything is based on
those realizations are based on
something you have to realize that in
tibetan in Buddhist uh perceptual
Theory Foundation is a word for
what objects objects because the
perception rests on the object you see
like if there's a glass of lemonade with
ice your visual perception rests on it
you see it's there and then you come
along and you perceive it right so that
you can't have the perception without
the glass of
lemonade okay
once you got the lemonade the perception
is triggered so in a sense the the
perception rests upon the lemonade on
the object so 10 often means like
Foundation but also the object
okay of course if you're in
tantric if you're in what did we talk
about last class
sub which came first the visual
Consciousness or the glass of lemonade
is it like everybody thinks that the
Lemonade's there and then it triggers
your perception of
it or is it that you're projecting the
lemonade after the Consciousness and in
a sense the the awareness of the
lemonade creates the
lemonade you see that makes Tantra
possible you see that you're not
perceiving vaji yogini
you're projecting
her that that makes vajin that makes it
possible for us to become vagini but
anyway we're in Sut right now so I can't
talk about that
uh okay by the way my idea I was
thinking about it that the inth courses
should be like halfway to Tantra and
then you know you just naturally bridge
to the tantric series from that you know
but we'll talk about that so like I'm
thinking that in the in-depth courses
which will be like I don't know how many
but there's the 18 basic courses Sutra
open courses but then by the time you
get to the in-depth courses I think you
should be mixing in a little bit of
Tantra and then you go all the way with
the 18 Tantra courses you see so I've
been doing that you might noticed okay
Foundation La Rick to that we sh we
what
sh call that's what we call
Rick okay you want to know what Rick is
it's that object which is based on you
can get into those six perceptions those
six realizations you want to know what
Buddha nature is you want to know what
we call Buddha nature we give that name
to La okay that object or Foundation
which provides the basis for those six
realizations which is
what the emptiness of those six
realizations The Emptiness of your own
mind okay you want to know what Buddha
nature is it's that emptiness which is
the foundation of those other six
realizations is AA coming up with this
on his own or is he pulling it out of
somewhere
ostensively he's getting it from my yeah
but my TR as you'll notice is is drawing
a lot on Gama yes from the 20,000 verses
especially a lot of what my tra ever
taught can be found in the 20,000 verses
I think he was trying to honor the
previous Buddha you see it's almost like
his Guru the last Buddha he's like
honoring the last Buddha so for Mya Gama
is the last buha right but he uses so
anyway you can see how this comes
directly from the quotation before okay
um this is a take on the previous
quotation especially because there are
13 different realizations mentioned I
only gave you the first six the dot dot
dot is the mixing missing seven okay
which are in your reading when you get
okay yeah what is J oh Juke means get
into
enter what's
body entering the ways of the
bodh okay uh you okay got anything okay
okay I'm going to give you one more
scriptural quotation to blow away your
uh friends with and then uh of course
they use their own quotations right but
we don't have to talk much about that
um where's this last one and then we'll
take a break we'll have some lemonade if
you can create
it come
I'm
sorry sh
say
CH say
y it's like V you know
that okay it looks like J right but it
changes to Y under certain circumstances
so it's y okay
y okay what we call Buddha nature same
thing as last quotation right what we
call Buddha nature we first la
Kaa
only to the
essence the the very essence okay I'll
say it again what we call Buddha nature
refers only Kona to the very
essence okay the very essence of the
ching ching is
dhad that's dhad it means The Ether of
all things you know the realm of all
things it's a word for
emptiness okay it's a word for
emptiness you know the the Ying of all
things okay and it was meant to be an
you know y
okay uh so that's pretty blunt okay you
want to know what Rick is it's emptiness
only nothing else okay who said that har
badra uh I'll write it for you
[Music]
uh
800s we don't know exactly when
but in tibetan
s s is an interesting word it's a
Corruption of a sing Sanskrit word
what
sing uh which is the word where
Singapore comes from por means town or
Village uh yeah lion the village of the
lion Singa uh sing okay anyway har he's
famous because he wrote the greatest
explanation of Arya and mraa that ever
existed he wrote two commentaries called
the Great commentary and the Lesser
commentary but and that ever any Indian
whoever wrote about after aanga whoever
wrote about a s m it was badra okay and
the lineage is like that you know you
get Lord Buddha teaching the Perfection
of w wisdom then you get mraa teaching
it going over it with Arya sa okay get
it straight now then Hari badra comments
on that then Jets Kaa comments on them
and then you get our textbooks s
textbooks sah J textbooks other great
textbooks okay but that's the Perfection
of wisdom lineage so what we're doing is
we've gone up through all the Indian
sources that would be accepted by all
Tibetan schools okay so that's pretty
clear you know so that ends the
sources okay and next we'll go on to
rang luk which is if you open up a cemon
textbook and you study the section
called Buddha nature what's the
definition of Buddha nature how many
kinds of Buddha nature are there what
are the examples of Buddha nature okay
we'll go through that and then to keep
you aake because it'll be late by then
we'll go through the tant presentation
of Buddha nature which is kind of cool
I'm not going to give you the whole
thing but just sort of a what do you
call it cookie cookie teaser yeah teaser
is good okay so we'll have a break you
want to do a little now
[Music]
okay have a nice break